Guide to the John Hope Franklin papers, 1891-2010, bulk 1950-2010 RL.10029
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Engagements (E), 1940-2009, and undated; 18 boxes
  - 1995-1997 (Box E9)
    Notable engagements in this box include: Race in America discussions with Vice President Al Gore, 1995; Prairie View A and M University Race, Ethnicity and the Problem of Human Rights Symposium, 1995; Tulane University Plessy Conference, 1996; Eric Williams Conference in Trinidad, 1996; North Carolina Central University Salute to John Hope Franklin, 1997; Morgan State University Quarles Memorial Lecture, 1997.
    Photographs included in folders: 1995 January 80th Birthday Commemoration; 1995 October; 1995 October 13-14 Prairie View A&M University Race, Ethnicity, and Problem of Human Rights; 1996 March; 1996 July; and 1997 June.
  - 1998-1999 March (Box E10)
    Notable engagements in this box include: Trip to Brazil, 1998; Supreme Court Historical Society lecture, 1998; Race and Reconciliation: Tutu and Franklin in Senegal, 1998.
    Photographs included in folders: 1998 March, and 1998 September 4 American Political Science Association Annual Meeting.
  - 1999 April-2000 September (Box E11)
    Notable engagements in this box include: Duke University Race and Representation Conference, 1999; New York University Slave Routes: The Long Memory Symposium, 1999; Trip to Brazil, 1999; Stanford University Conference on Race, 1999.
  - 2000 October-2003 June (Box E12)
    Notable engagements in this box include: U.S. Department of State trip to South Africa, 2001; Library of Congress John W. Kluge Fellow, 2001-2003; Trip to Mali, 2002; The Citadel Conference on the Civil Rights Movement in South Carolina, 2003; University of Chicago Symposium to Honor John Hope Franklin, 2003.
    Photographs included in folders: 2000 October 25-27 Northwestern University, 2001 March 6-23 U.S. Department of State Trip to South Africa, 2001 June 23 Wedding of K. Mack and L. Jones, 2001 August, 2001 October 16 Ohio Statehouse George Washington Williams Memorial Room, and 2003 May.
  - 2003 July-2009 (Box E13)
    Notable engagements in this box include: 90th birthday celebration, 2005.
    Photographs included in folders: 2004, 2005 March, 2005 November, and 2006 April.
  - Telephone messages, frequent flyer statements, travel agency receipts, and compiled lists of engagements (Box E13)
  - Day planners (Box E14)
  - Additional Engagements Series materials, 1951-2001 and undated; 15 folders (Box E15)
    Materials received as an addition to the collection include programs, correspondence, clippings, and photographs. Materials of note: a 1951 day planner with many engagement entries from a summer-long trip to Europe that included the Salzburg Seminar in American Studies, where JHF gave a series of lectures; a 1955 program from the University of Rochester, NY student conference on "The Freedom to Dissent," at which JHF was a keynote speaker; photographs, a letter, and text of JHF's convocation speech at San Jose State University, 1967; and photographs from the opening of the JHF Research Center at Duke University, 2001.
    Photographs from the 1951 Salzburg Seminar in American Studies and postcards from the Franklin's European tour are found in the Travel subseries in the Research, Biographical, and Subject Files series.
  - Additional Engagements Series materials, 2001-2008 and undated (Box E16)
    Items of interest include: photographs from the opening of the JHF Research Center at Duke University, 2001; photographs and other materials from the Obama election campaign, 2006-2008.
  - Photograph album with various professional portraits, 1964-1975 and undated (Box E17)
    Album containing 21 8x10 format black-and-white photographic portraits of Franklin during his tenure at Brooklyn College, and at various ceremonies. Images from Brooklyn show him teaching, posing with students, and standing with Arthur W. Secord, English literary scholar and professor born and raised in Oklahoma. Most prints have captions on the backs or written on the pages; the handwriting appears to be Aurelia Franklin's.
  - Photograph and memento album, Bethune Cookman College commencement, Daytona Beach, Florida, JHF as keynote speaker, 1998 April (Box E17)
    Album contains 16 color snapshots of the processional, Franklin giving the keynote address, and group shots, most with detailed captions. Also includes a letter from the college, many photocopied clippings, and a photocopy of the program.
  - Publicity/clippings: Brooklyn College Kingsman, article about History Department, JHF as Chair, 1959 February (Box E18)
    Original copy is fragile; photocopy is provided in folder.
  - Publicity/clippings, 1970s (Box E18)
  - Publicity/clippings, 1980s (Box E18)
  - Publicity/clippings, 1990s; 2 folders (Box E18)
  - Publicity/clippings, 2000s (Box E18)
  - Publicity photographs, Ebony magazine article on JHF, circa 1987; 6 photographs 1 folder (Box OV4)
    11x14 black-and-white prints show JHF at his desk, cultivating orchids, and other scenes.
  - Events posters, various, 1999-2009; 6 items 4 unique items and 2 duplicates (Box OV4)
  - Franklin at Duke basketball game, color photographs, 2001 (Box OV4)
    1 11x14 color print and several 8x12 color prints of Franklin wearing a Duke sweatshirt, posing with President Keohane, and standing, waving. One contact sheet with black-and-white images also shows Bill Cosby speaking at the same event. Photographs were taken by a Duke University photographer.
  - Posters from the Harvard Law School related to 50th anniversary of Brown vs. Board of Education, 2003; 3 items (Box OV6)
- Honors and Awards (H), 1952-2010; 8 boxes and several oversize folders
  Arranged chronologically by year within the two subseries, with oversize materials removed to Box H7, Boxes OV1 and OV2, and Oversize Folder 1.
  This series includes files pertaining to the many honors and awards Franklin earned throughout his life. There are two subseries in Honors and Awards: Honorary Degrees and General Awards.
  - Honorary Degrees, 1960-2006
    John Hope Franklin received over 140 honorary degrees in his lifetime. The folders in this series typically include correspondence surrounding the logistics of the ceremony, programs and bulletins from the event, press coverage, the actual diploma or certificate that Franklin received, and thank you notes from Franklin and the other participants.
    The files offer glimpses of the different campuses Franklin visited throughout the mid-twentieth century, at times revealing the turmoil and tensions accompanying the civil rights movement and Vietnam War protests. Some files include photographs and have been noted below. Other files include copies of commencement speeches given by Franklin at various graduation ceremonies.
    Oversize diplomas have been removed to Box H7, where they are foldered by decade.
    - 1960 (Box H2)
      Morgan State University.
    - 1961 (Box H2)
      Virginia State University, Lincoln University.
    - 1962 (Box H2)
      Morris Brown, University of Cambridge.
    - 1964 (Box H2)
      Tuskegee Institute, Long Island University, University of Massachusetts.
    - 1965 (Box H2)
      Hamline University, Lincoln College.
    - 1966 (Box H2)
      Fisk University.
    - 1967 (Box H2)
      Rhode Island College, Tougaloo College.
    - 1968 (Box H2)
      Johnston C. Smith University, Dickinson College, Howard University.
    - 1969 (Box H2)
      Morehouse College, Loyola University, Arizona State University, Kalamazoo College (includes photographs), Bard College, Drake University, Wilmington College, Michigan State University, Governors State College.
    - 1970 (Box H2)
      Columbia University (includes photographs), University of Maryland (includes photographs), University of Notre Dame, University of Illinois.
    - 1972 (Box H2)
      University of Tulsa, Princeton University, Northwestern University, Chicago City College.
    - 1973 (Box H2)
      Catholic University, Marquette University, Lake Forest College, Brown University, Miami University (OH).
    - 1974 (Box H2)
      Temple University, Trinity College, University of the State of New York.
    - 1975 (Box H2)
      Tulane University, Washington University in St. Louis, Whittier College, Brooklyn College.
    - 1976 (Box H2)
      Carnegie Mellon University, Boston College, Grand Valley State Colleges, Union College.
    - 1977 (Box H2)
      University of Michigan, Seattle University, University of Toledo, Stanford University, Yale University.
    - 1978 (Box H2)
      Roosevelt University (includes photographs), College of New Rochelle, Governors State University. University of Utah (includes photos), Wayne State University, Northern Michigan University.
    - 1978, continued (Box H3)
      University of Utah (includes photographs), Wayne State University, Northern Michigan University.
    - 1979 (Box H3)
      Dillard University, University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.
    - 1980 (Box H3)
      Manhattan College.
    - Manhattan College scrapbook, 1980 May 18 (Box H1)
    - 1981 (Box H3)
      Ripon College, Harvard University (includes photographs), University of Pennsylvania, Atlanta University. Oversize diploma for U. Penn housed in Box OV1.
    - 1982 (Box H3)
      Indiana State University, St. Olaf's College, North Carolina Central University (includes photograph).
    - 1983 (Box H3)
      University of Miami, Emory University, University of North Carolina at Charlotte.
    - 1984 (Box H3)
      University of Connecticut.
    - 1985 (Box H3)
      Brandeis University (includes photographs).
    - 1986 (Box H3)
      Wake Forest University.
    - 1987 (Box H3)
      Wilkes College, Queens College.
    - 1988 (Box H3)
      Hope College (includes photograph), Bryant College, SUNY Binghamton, Indiana University, North Carolina Wesleyan.
    - 1989 (Box H3)
      Berea College, CUNY Graduate School, Southern Methodist University, Suffolk University.
    - 1990 (Box H3)
      Washington College, University of North Carolina at Greensboro, Eckerd College, Rutgers.
    - 1991 (Box H3)
      Georgetown University, Winston-Salem State University, Oregon State University, St. Augustine's College.
    - 1992 (Box H3)
      Illinois State University, Bates College, Queen's College (NC), Williams College, University of the South.
    - 1993 (Box H3)
      American University, University of North Carolina at Wilmington.
    - 1994 (Box H3)
      University of Oklahoma, George Washington University (includes photograph), North Carolina State University, Tufts University, Columbia College Chicago.
    - 1995 (Box H3)
      Furman University (includes photographs).
    - 1996 (Box H4)
      Elizabeth City State University, Shaw University, University of San Francisco, Washington and Lee University.
    - 1997 (Box H4)
      Lane College, Roosevelt University, Elmira College.
    - 1998 (Box H4)
      Bethune-Cookman College, University of Kentucky, Occidental College, Duke University, University of North Carolina at Greensboro, Amherst College, Cal State University/San Francisco University, York College (CUNY), University of Cincinnati, Dartmouth College, Northeastern University, University of North Carolina at Pembroke.
    - 1999 (Box H4)
      Millsaps College, Penn State University, University of Vermont, University of San Diego, DePaul University.
    - 2000 (Box H4)
      Texas A&M University, Bennett College, Pomona College, University of South Florida, Edinboro University of Pennsylvania.
    - 2001 (Box H4)
      University of North Carolina at Asheville, New Jersey City University.
    - 2002 (Box H4)
      Davidson College.
    - 2004 (Box H4)
      University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign.
    - 2005 (Box H4)
      South Carolina State University, University of the District of Columbia.
    - 2006 (Box H4)
      LaFayette College, Wesleyan University.
  - General Awards and Honors, 1952-2010
    This subseries typically includes correspondence announcing the award, logistical information about the ceremony, publicity, and the actual certificate. Some notable awards, particularly the Presidential Medal of Freedom (1995), also include files of congratulatory notes. Many original wooden or metal plaques have been removed from the collection, but color photocopies have been made and filed in their place. Digital photographs of the original plaque are available for researchers if needed. Paper certificates have been retained. Oversize certificates have been removed to Box H7, Oversize Folder 1, or Box OV1 and OV2.
    The General Awards subseries has been foldered chronologically. Those awards which included a lot of accompanying materials have been foldered individually by event. Miscellaneous awards are grouped by year.
    - Brown University President's Fellowship, 1952 (Box H5)
    - Phi Beta Kappa induction certificate, 1953 (Box H7)
    - General awards, 1960, 1964-1966, 4 folders (Box H5)
    - Middle States Council for the Social Studies gold medal, 1968 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1968, 1969, 1971-1973, 5 folders (Box H5)
    - NAACP Legal Defense Fund tribute, 1974 (Box H5)
      Includes photographs.
    - Association of St. Louis University Libraries Wilma and Roswell Messing Award, 1975 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1975-1977, 3 folders (Box H5)
    - Oklahoma Hall of Fame, 1978, 2 folders (Box H5)
      Oversize certificate from this event has been housed in Box H7.
    - General awards, 1978 (Box H5)
    - Fisk University creates the John Hope Franklin Chair, 1979, 3 folders (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1979 (Box H5)
    - Lincoln Academy Laureate (Illinois), 1980 (Box H5)
    - Retirement from University of Chicago, 1980 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1980 (Box H5)
    - Abraham Lincoln Centre, Chicago, Humanitarian Service Award, 1982 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1982, 1983 (Box H5)
    - Council for Advancement and Support of Education (CASE) Jefferson Medal, 1984, 2 folders (Box H5)
    - Illinois Humanities Council Public Humanities Award, 1984 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1984 (Box H5)
    - Fisk University Jubilee Medallion, 1985 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1985 (Box H5)
    - UCLA Medal, 1986 (Box H5)
    - NYPL Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture Clarence Holte Literary Prize, 1986 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1986 (Box H5)
    - Blackbook's Humanitarian Award, 1987 (Box H5)
    - Associated Black Charities Black History Makers Award, 1988 (Box H5)
    - Black Educators calendar with JHF portrait, 1988 (Box OV5)
    - Miller Brewing Company Gallery of Greats calendar, 1988 (Box H5)
      Oversize calendars housed in Box OV2.
    - General awards, 1988 (Box H5)
    - Fellowship of Southern Writers Cleanth Brooks Medal, 1989 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1989 (Box H5)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica Award, 1990 (Box H5)
      Oversize certificate housed in Box H7.
    - General awards, 1990 (Box H5)
    - Morehouse College Candle in the Dark, 1991 (Box H5)
    - NC Humanities Council John Tyler Caldwell Award, 1991 (Box H5)
    - General awards, 1991 (Box H5)
    - UNC Chapel Hill University Medal, 1992 (Box H5)
    - Duke University Award, 1992 (Box H6)
    - General awards, 1992 (Box H6)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities Charles Frankel Prize, 1993, 2 folders (Box H6)
    - North Carolina Award, 1993 (Box H6)
    - National Emergency Civil Liberties Union Clark Foreman Award, 1993 (Box H6)
    - General awards, 1993 (Box H6)
    - NAACP North Carolina Lelly Alexander Award, 1994 (Box H6)
    - Phi Beta Kappa Sidney Hook Memorial Award, 1994 (Box H6)
    - Turner Broadcasting Trumpet Award, 1994 (Box H6)
    - Cosmos Club Award, 1994 (Box H6)
    - General awards, 1994 (Box H6)
    - Trumpet of Conscience Annual Breakfast, 1995 (Box H6)
    - NAACP Spingarn Medal, 1995 (Box H6)
    - Presidential Medal of Freedom, 1995, 5 folders (Box H6)
      Oversize certificate housed in Box OV2. Oversize photograph housed in Oversize Folder 2.
    - General awards, 1995 (Box H6)
    - Smithsonian National Museum of American History Lifetime Achievement Award, 1996 (Box H6)
    - Strong Men and Women Award from Virginia/NC Power, 1996 (Box H6)
    - NC Historian of the Century, 1996 (Box H6)
    - General awards, 1996 (Box H6)
    - Durham Symphony Tribute, 1997 (Box H6)
    - Duke University portrait unveiling, 1997 (Box H6)
    - Booker T. Washington High School Hall of Fame, 1997 (Box H6)
    - Johnston C. Smith University Circle of Honor Award, 1997 (Box H6)
    - Tulsa City-County Library Distinguished Author Award, 1997 (Box H6)
    - General awards, 1997 (Box H8)
    - Oklahoma Book Awards, 1998 (Box H8)
    - UNC Greensboro Founders Day McIver Award, 1998 (Box H8)
    - Lincoln Forum Award of Achievement, 1998 (Box H8)
    - NAACP Legal Defense Fund Equal Justice Award, 1998 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 1998 (Box H8)
    - 84th Birthday Celebration, 1999 (Box H8)
    - Harry S. Truman Good Neighbor Award, 1999 (Box H8)
    - Durham Committee on the Affairs of Black People 64th Anniversary Founders Banquet, 1999 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 1999 (Box H8)
    - Skirball Institute Award, 2000 (Box H8)
    - Union College NY Lincoln Prize, 2000, 2 folders (Box H8)
    - Harold Washington Literary Prize, 2000 (Box H8)
    - Bode-Pearson Award American Studies, 2000 (Box H8)
    - National Medal of Arts and National Humanities dinner, 2000 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 2000 (Box H8)
    - International Visitor's Council Citizen of the World, 2001 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 2001 (Box H8)
    - UC Berkeley Clark Kerr Award, 2002 (Box H8)
    - American Academy of Arts and Sciences Gold Medal in History, 2002 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 2002-2003, 2 folders (Box H8)
    - Birmingham Civil Rights Institute, 2004 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 2004 (Box H8)
    - Fisk University "Celebrating a tradition of excellence" poster of notable alumni, with JHF portrait and caption, 2005 (Box OV8)
    - North Caroliniana Society Tribute, 2005 (Box H8)
    - General awards, 2006, 2009, undated, 4 folders (Box H8)
    - Awards and honors named for Franklin, 1987-1993, 2004 (Box H8)
    - City of Chicago, Harold Washington Literary Award, 2000 (Box OV5)
    - "Tar Heel of the Year," Raleigh News and Observer (color reproduction), 1998 (Box OV5)
    - Kentucky and Virginia state resolutions, 2009, 2010; 2 items (Box OV5)
- Personal and Family Materials (P), 1891-2000s; 1930-2009; 9 boxes and many oversize folders
  Series comprises materials relating to Franklin's life and pursuits outside of his scholarship and public service. It also includes materials from other family members, particularly his wife, Aurelia Whittington Franklin, whose papers span several boxes; their son, John Whittington "Whit" Franklin; and Franklin's father, Buck Colbert Franklin.
  The materials have been organized by family member, and within, in rough chronological order. A sizable amount of materials have been classified more generally as "Franklin Family." This group contains a large amount of photographs of family and friends, many of which are snapshots of casual scenes. Miscellaneous photographs of family friends have not been arranged. Photographs of family members, particularly John Hope, Aurelia, and John W. Franklin, have been sorted by decade, with a large file of miscellaneous and undated photographs remaining. Photographs have been sleeved for preservation, with labels left visible if present.
  Franklin's professor and mentor, Theodore Currier, is also represented in this series, stemming from Franklin's role as executor following Currier's death in 1979. Materials relate to the estate settlement, but also include Currier memorabilia such as diplomas (1920-1928), Currier's high school yearbook, and other items.
  The series also includes an original painting by the French artist Georges Bigot, who worked in Japan in the late nineteenth century. It included no accompanying contextual information but appears to have been part of Franklin's art collection. It is filed in under John Hope Franklin's subseries.
  - Burney, David (JHF's grandfather)
    - Pension application (photocopy), 1891 (Box P1)
  - Currier, Theodore S. (JHF's professor and mentor), 1920-1990
    Materials were assembled by John Hope Franklin chiefly through his role as estate executor following Currier's death in 1979.
    - Currier's high school diploma, teaching certificate, and Master's degree diploma, 1920, 1924, 1928 (Box OV8)
    - The Gleam, 1927 yearbook (Massachusetts) (Box P1)
    - Photographs and scrapbook, 1920s (Box P1)
    - Honors and awards (Box P1)
    - Teaching career at Fisk University (Box P1)
    - Will, memorials, obituaries (Box P1)
    - Estate disposition and beneficiaries, 1980-1990, 5 folders (Box P1)
    - Blueprint surveys of two Currier estate lots in Maine, 1981 (Box OV8)
  - D'Ndaiye, Bouna (JHF's adopted son)
    - Visa materials, 2002 (Box P1)
  - Fitzsimmons, Margaret (JHF's longtime assistant)
    - Personnel materials, 1975-1995 (Box P1)
  - Franklin family (general), 1950s-2000s
    - For Better or For Worse, 1999 (Box P1)
      Includes copies of JHF and AWF's co-written love story, as well as photographs used in the printing of the publication.
    - Address cards, 2 folders (Box P1)
    - Recipes (Box P1)
    - Christmas cards, 1950s-1980s (Box P1)
    - Photographs, 1950s (Box P1)
    - Photographs from European trip, 1951 (Box P1)
    - Photographs, 1960s, 2 folders (Box P1)
      Includes photographs from Cambridge, Brooklyn, and Chicago, among others.
    - Photographs, 1980s (Box P1)
    - Hampton University reunion photographs, 1980 and 1990 (Box P1)
    - Marian Bennett (goddaughter) visit photographs, 1996 (Box P1)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, 1970s-2000s (Box P1)
      Photographs (including snapshots and formal portraits) of family members, often undated.
    - Travel photographs, undated (Box P2)
    - Miscellaneous photographs of friends, 1970s-2000s, 5 folders (Box P2)
      Snapshots and other photographs sent to or collected by the Franklins of their many friends and acquaintances, including some Christmas cards and school portraits. Some photographs date from events or engagements featuring John Hope Franklin, but may be undated or unlabeled.
    - Oversize photographs of family friends (Box P5)
      Includes oversize White House Christmas card from the Clintons.
    - Oversize photographs, undated (Box OV3)
  - Franklin, Aurelia Whittington (JHF's wife), 1931-1999
    - Address cards, 2 folders (Box P2)
    - Publicity and clippings (Box P2)
    - Honors and awards (Box P2)
    - Miscellaneous cards and notes (Box P2)
    - Washington High School Echo yearbook (Raleigh), 1943 (Box P2)
    - NC College yearbook, 1946 (Box P2)
    - Library school notes and texts, 1949-1950 and undated, 2 folders (Box P2)
      Many additional folders with library school coursework and records are found in box P7.
    - Librarianship, 1940s-1960s, 2 folders (Box P2)
    - Church life, 1960s (Box P2)
    - Cambridge, 1962-1963 (Box P2)
    - University of Chicago Laboratory Schools, 1964-1966 (Box P2)
    - IT Club, 1965-1969 (Box P2)
    - Department of Children and Family Services Advisory Board, Illinois, 1969-1971 (Box P2)
    - Department of Children and Family Services commission certificates, Illinois, 3 items 2 certificates and a letter (Box OV5)
    - Bob Roberts Service Committee, 1981 (Box P2)
    - Triangle Park Civic League, 1984 (Box P2)
    - NC Museum of Art Board of Directors, 1987 (Box P2)
    - Lists of sympathy cards sent to JHF after Aurelia's death, 1999 (Box P2)
    - Memorials and tributes, 1999 (Box P2)
    - Additional library school records and notes, 1939-1952; 17 folders (Box P7)